Finding aid for the Sam Balter papers LSC.2266
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sam Balter papers
circa 1930s-circa 1970s (bulk 1943-1964)
1943-1964
UCLA Library Special Collections
Balter, Sam (1909-)
LSC.2266
10.4 linear feet (15 boxes, 1 shoe box, 2 cartons, and 3 flat boxes)
Sam Balter was a sportscaster, hosting One for the Book feature sports commentary on the Mutual Network and sports columnist for the Los Angeles Herald-Express. The collection consists of materials related to Sam Balter's career, including scripts from his KLAC radio sports program One for the Book and clippings of his newspaper sports column, One for the Book, written for the Los Angeles Herald Express. Also included is correspondence from listeners and readers and a small amount of ephemera, books, sports-related wire service and newspaper clippings, and audio recordings.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sam and Mildred Balter, 1994
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9979941863606533
Biography/History
Sam Balter was born October 15, 1909 in Detroit, Michigan. He was selected as a UCLA all-American basketball player (1929) and was chosen for first U.S. Olympic Basketball Team, which won the gold medal in 1936. He was the only Jewish American gold medalist at Games in Berlin. In 1938, he broadcast the first U.S. coast-to-coast radio sports commentary on the Mutual Network. During World War II, he worked as a broadcaster for the Los Angeles-based KFWB and KFI. He broadcast play-by-play for the Cincinnati Reds baseball team (1942), was known as the voice of the UCLA Bruins football and basketball radiocasts (1945-1952), and was an announcer for baseball Pacific Coast League Hollywood Stars and Los Angeles Angels, and the Los Angeles Stars of the American Basketball Association.
From 1946 to 1962 he was sports director for KLAC and roughly during the same time he broadcast a weekly One for the Book radio feature that covered a wide range of sports. From 1955-1962, Balter published a daily One for the Book newspaper column for the Los Angeles Herald-Express, and in 1955 published the book, One for the Book of Sports with co-author Cy Rice. He was the recipient of numerous professional honors, among them Variety's Top Sportscaster in the Country (1953). He was also elected to the Basketball Hall of Fame (1970), the International Jewish Sports Hall of Fame (1994), the Southern California Broadcasters Hall of Fame, and UCLA Athlete Hall of Fame. Sam Balter died August 8, 1998.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the career of broadcaster and newspaper columnist Sam Balter. Included are scripts from his KLAC radio sports program One for the Book as well as clippings of his newspaper sports column, One for the Book, written for the Los Angeles Herald-Express. Also included is correspondence from listeners and readers and a small amount of writings by Balter (outside of his radio and newspaper columns), ephemera, books, sports-related wire service and newspaper clippings, and audio recordings. The bulk of correspondence documents Balter's work as a news commentator for KFWB and KFI radio stations during the mid-1940s. Additionally, there is a small amount of correspondence with clippings regarding the Pacific Coast Conference's probation and penalties imposed on UCLA's athletic program in 1956. Most of the ephemera, books, newspaper clippings, and audio recordings are sports related.
Notably absent from the collection are materials related to Balter's participation in the 1936 Berlin Olympics as a member of the first U.S. basketball team and material representing his play-by-play radio and television sports broadcasting.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Series 1. One for the Book
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Writings by Balter
Series 4. Sports Ephemera and Publications
Series 5. Books and Record Albums.
Sports journalism -- United States.; Radio broadcasters -- Archives.; Balter, Sam (1909-) -- Archives
- One for the Book, Undated [circa 1955-circa 1963]
  Scope and Content
  The series documents Balter's radio and Los Angeles Herald newspaper commentary feature, One for the Book. Included are numbered radio scripts and published newspaper columns representing a wide variety of sports-related topics such as basketball, boxing, baseball, football, horseracing and track and field. The scripts are numbered but not dated; notably absent are script numbers 682-702.
  Organization and Arrangement
  The series is arranged with scripts first ,in number order, followed by published clippings in loose chronological order.
  - One for the Book list (appears to segment titles for feature sports commentary), (undated) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - One for the Book unnumbered scripts and notes, (undated) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 1-25, (undated) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 26-50, (undated) (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 51-75, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 76-100, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 101-125, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 126-150, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 151-175, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 176-200, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 201-225, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 226-250, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 251-275, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 276-300, (undated) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 301-325, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 326-350, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 351-375, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 376-400, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 401-425, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 426-450, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 451-475, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 476-500, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 501-525, (undated) (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 526-550, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 551-575, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 576-600, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 626-650, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 601-625, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 651-675, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 676-682, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 700-725, (undated) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 726-750, (undated) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 751-775, (undated) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 776-800, (undated) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 801-825, (undated) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 826-850, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 851-864, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 865-875, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 876-900, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 901-925, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - One for the Book radio scripts, numbers 926-942, (undated) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - One for the Book columns in scrapbook, (1955 June 15-Feb. 14, 1957) (Box 15)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1957 Feb. 23-June) (Box 16)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1958 Jan-June) (Box 16)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1958 July-Dec) (Box 16)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1959 Jan-June) (Box 16)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1959 July-Dec) (Box 16)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1960 Jan-June) (Box 17)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1960 July-Dec) (Box 17)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1961 Jan-June) (Box 17)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (1961 July-Dec) (Box 17)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (circa 1962 Jan-circa 1963 June and undated) (Box 17)
  - One for the Book columns (published clippings), (circa 1963 July-Dec and undated) (Box 17)
- Correspondence, 1943-1976 (bulk dates 1944-1959); 1944-1959
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  The series consists of letters to Sam Balter, mostly from listeners and readers, and documents his career working as a radio news commentator on Los Angeles based radio stations KWFB and KFI during World War II; his radio sports feature, One for the Book; and his Los Angeles Herald column One for the Book. The letters reflect audience support and/or reaction to Balter's commentary on a wide variety of current events of the time. Additionally there are letters protesting Balter's dismissal from KFWB and KFI for what was thought to be liberal political views during World War II and a small amount of material regarding the Pacific Coast Commission's penalties and probation against the UCLA Football program (1956).
  - Letters to Balter, (1943-1976) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Possible exhibit item.
    With a 1943 letter from a Army Air Corps Capt. Worth E. Ober Jr., who was a part of the air campaign against Japan.
  - KFWB Listener letters, (1944 Feb-May) (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - KFWB Listener protest letters, (1944 April ) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    With letter from Congressman George E. Outland regarding the firing of Sam Balter from Mutual Network in 1944.
  - KFWB Listener letters (3 folders), (1944 May-July ) (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - KFI and KFWB Listener letters (5 folders), (1944 May-July) (Box 1, Folder 10-11, Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - KFI and KFWB Listener letters, (1944 Oct-Nov) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - KFWB Listener letters (3 folders), (1945) (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - KFWB Listener letters, (1945 Jan-June) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - KFI Listener letters protesting Balter's dismissal from Mutual Network (2 folders), (1945 Feb-May) (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Listener letters (2 folders), (1945 July-Oct) (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    Possible exhibit item
    Copy of letter from the House of Representatives U.S. Committee on Un-American Activities to Mrs. Rose Corn (1946)
  - Sports Quiz Bowl submissions, (1946 Dec-1947 Feb) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - KLAC Sports Listener letters (3 folders), (1946-1950) (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Listener letters (4 folders), (1951) (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 8-10)
    With fan letter to Balter from Kirk Douglas.
  - Listener letters (3 folders), (1951-1953) (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    With letter to Balter from Patricia Thorpe, widow of Jim Thorpe.
  - Listener letters regarding wrestler Baron Leone, (1952 May) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sports Forum Listener letters, (1953 Aug) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Listener letters, (1954) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Listener and Reader letters (2 folders), (1954-1956) (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    With letter to Balter from Goose Tatum and Marques Haynes (former Harlem Globe Trotters).
  - Listener and Reader letters, and articles regarding Pacific Coast Commission probation and penalties against UCLA Football (4 folders), (1956) (Box 11, Folder 10, Box 4, Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Exhibit item
    Speech by Chancellor Raymond B. Allen.
    With transcript of speech by Dr. Raymond B. Allen, UCLA Chancellor, presented for the Commonwealth Club, San Francisco, June 8, 1956, and copies of letters to Robert Sproul, Edwin Pauley, and Govenor Goodwin Knight.
  - Listener and Reader letters (2 folders), (1957-1959) (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Herman Weiner correspondence regarding claims against Balter, (1958 Aug-Sept) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Listener and Reader letters (2 folders), (1958-1959) (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
  - Boxing - letters, clippings and wire service printouts, (1959-1960) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Listener and Reader letters (2 folders), (1959-1961) (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
    General
    With letter to Sam Balter from Los Angeles Rams owner Daniel Reeves.
  - John F. Kennedy death, (1963) (Box 12, Folder 7)
    With One for the Book column, excerpt from Balter broadcast, reader and listener letters, and publications.
- Writings by Balter, (1932-1970)
  There is no specific arrangement to the series.
  The series consists of writings by Sam Balter outside of his radio and newspaper column, One for the Book. Included is a work titled Forty Years of Olympic Basketball; a possible writing project focused on basketball coaching; writings about John F. Kennedy; and uncredited writing that may have been penned by Sam Balter.
  - Assorted writings and notes by Sam Balter, (1958 and undated) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - [Basketball writing project?], (1932-1937) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Holographic and typescript pages that may be related to a 1937 writing project by Sam Balter titled, Basketball Without the Center Jump.
  - Forty Years of Olympic Basketball by Sam Balter, (undated) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Sam Balter Sportsbook press release, award, (undated) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sports Ephemera and Publications, circa 1937-circa 1980
  The series are arranged alphabetically by file titles.
  The series consists of ephemera and publications mostly related to Southern California based sports teams. Included are press publications, souvenir programs, wire service printouts, and a small number of press releases. The bulk of the items are associated with the Dodgers, the Lakers, the Los Angeles Stars, and UCLA sports. There is a small number of items representing the Harlem Globe Trotters, the Hollywood Stars, the Rams, and the Washington Caps. Additionally, there are undated wire service copy covering a wide range of sports feature material and a very small number of 1980s Olympics' memorabilia.
  - 16th Annual National Collegiate Basketball Championship program, (1954) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1839 /1939 Baseball League Centennial sleeve patch, [circa 1939] (Box 21)
  - Baseball published ephemera, (1947-1969) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Basketball published ephemera, 1937-1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Douglas Guardian periodicals, (1956-1960) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Harlem Globe Trotters souvenir program, (1953-1954) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Helms Athletic Foundation press releases, reports and sports features, (circa 1960s) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Hollywood Stars decals (7 items, duplicates), (undated) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Los Angeles Angels decal (1 item), (undated) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Los Angeles Dodgers publicity materials and ephemera (3 folders), (1947-1980) (Box 12, Folder 4-6)
  - Los Angeles Lakers Illustrated Yearbooks, (1962-1964) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Los Angeles Rams Official Yearbook, (1963) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Los Angeles Stars programs, (1969-1970) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - National Football League history publications (2 items), (undated) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - The Newspaper Credo of William Randolph Hearst, (undated) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Olympics related ephemera, (1980, 1984) (Box 21)
    1984 ribbons, one honoring Balter; mini Olympics souvenir flags from the 1980s; Squaw Valley souvenir.
  - Olympics press material and souvenir publication, (1952-1966) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Reflections on the Age of Anxiety - Audio History (record), (circa 1960s) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Rose Bowl: A Complete Action and Pictorial Exposition of Rose Bowl Football by Maxwell Stiles, (undated) (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Signed by Stiles to Balter.
  - Sports clippings and wire service printouts, (1961) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Sports filler wire service copy, (undated) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Sports humor and trivia, (undated) (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Sports press releases, (1956-1966) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Sports wire service copy (3 folders), (undated) (Box 13, Folder 1-2, Box 12, Folder 9)
    Covers a range of topics which have been used in part in Balter's radio and newspaper column One for the Book.
  - Sportscasters Association publications (2 items), (circa early-1960s) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Try and Stop Me: A Collection of Anecdotes and Stories, Mostly Humorous by Bennett Cerf, (1944-1953) (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - UCLA sports printed and published ephemera, (1958-1969) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    With publication titled How to Play Basketball by John R. Wooden.
    6X7.5" pamphlet by UCLa Basketball coach John Wooden on "How to Play Basketball"
  - Washington Caps published ephemera, (undated) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - What Were the Circumstances and What Were the Results of the Sale of Babe Ruth to the Yankees by the Red Sox in 1920? by Mervyn S. Harris - mimeograph of typescript, (1960) (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Books and Records Albums
  The series consists of books and records albums collected by Sam Balter. Included are hardbound, paperback, and pamphlet-like books along with a variety of commercially released record albums related to a variety of sports as well as humor.
  Books in Collection 2266 have been individually cataloged. They are discoverable in the UCLA Library online catalog by keyword searching the phrase: "Ex libris Sam Balter."
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audio materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Books from the library of Sam Balter (16 hardbound and 1 pamphlet books about a variety of sports topics), various dates (Box 19)
    To find individual titles, search the title: Sam Balter Papers.
  - Books from the Library of Sam Balter (34 hardbound, paperback and pamphlet books covering a variety of sports and humor topics), (1929-1960) (Box 20)
  - Balter reels II and III (5 inch audio reels), (undated) (Box 18)
  - Sam Balter for sports book transcription disc, (1954 March 19) (Box 18)
  - The Best of Allen Funt's Candid Mike, Vol. 1, LP 25 (33 1/3 RPM), (undated) (Box 18)
  - The Explosive Sounds of Pro Football narrated by Elroy Hirsch (33 1/3 RPM), (c. 1963) (Box 18)
    COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audio
  - Great Moments in Boxing (33 1/3 RPM), (undated) (Box 18)
    Written and produced by Bud Greenspan; narration by Don Dunphy.
  - The Greatest Moments in Sports actual sounds and voices (33 1/3 RPM), (1919-1954) (Box 18)
    Spoken passages by or about Lou Gehrig, Babe Ruth, Johnny Vandermeer, Connie Mack, Carl Hubbell, Bobby Thomson, Al Gionfriddo, Cookie Lavagetto, Knute Rockne, Jesse Owens, Roger Bannister, Glenn Cunningham, Helen Jacobs, Grantland Rice, Earl Sande, Josy Barthel, Roy Riegels, Jack Dempsey, Gene Tunney, Joe Louis, Jess Willard, Tony Galento, Jim Corbett; narrated by Clem McCarthy, Mel Allen, Don Dunphy, Marty Glickman.
  - Greatest Races of 1954 (33 1/3 RPM), (undated) (Box 18)
  - Guideposts Spots with Catherine Marshall and Red Barber (33 1/3 RPM), (c. 1966) (Box 18)
    COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Guideposts from the World of Sports told by Red Barber and Carol Heiss (33 1/3 RPM), (c. 1965) (Box 18)
  - How To Break 80...at Home! A Revolutionary New Method of Golf Instruction (33 1/3 RPM), (c. 1958) (Box 18)
    Written and directed by Dick Robb, PGA.
  - I Am the Greatest! Cassius Clay (33 1/3 RPM), (c. 1963) (Box 18)
  - Learn Bridge at Home with Robert Lee Johnson (2 LP 33 1/3 RPM), (c. 1958) (Box 18)
    Singed to Balter by Bob Johnson.
  - A No-Hitter for Bill Singer (33 1/3 RPM), (1970 July 20) (Box 18)
  - A Heart I Can't Give Away (45 RPM) and printed sheet music to Sam Balter from former student George Roncevich, (undated) (Box 18)
  - USAF Presents Tops in Sports featuring Harry Wisner (33 1/3 RPM) (U.S. Air Force Public Service Program) --, (undated) (Box 18)
    Show 1: The Oscar Robertson Story; Show 2: The Gene Tunney Story.
  - We Love the Dodgers as sung by Jimmie Maddin (45 RPM), (undated) (Box 18)
  - What is a Jew by Alex Dreier (45 RPM), (undated) (Box 18)